Guide to the United Automobile Workers of America, Local 2110, New York University Graduate Student Organizing Committee (GSOC) Records WAG.285
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United Automobile Workers of America, Local 2110, New York University Graduate Student Organizing Committee (GSOC) Records
1996-2003
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United Automobile Workers of America, Local 2110. New York University Graduate Student Organizing Committee
Adjuncts Come Together-United Auto Workers (ACT-UAW)
WAG.285
1 Linear Feet in one record carton and 1 oversize folder
13 websites in 13 archived websites.
The Graduate Student Organizing Committee (GSOC) represents graduate and research assistants at New York University (NYU) and is affiliated with the United Auto Workers Local 2110. GSOC was the first graduate employee union at a private university to successfully negotiate a contract. This collection contains materials pertaining to the GSOC organizing drive from 1998 to 2000, and the negotiation of GSOC's first contract with NYU in 2001. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence. Other materials include promotional flyers, newsletters, handwritten notes, surveys and labor education materials.
Related Archival Materials
United Automobile Workers of America, Local 2110, Professional and Administrative Staff Association (PASTA) of the Museum of Modern Art Records (WAG 174)
New York University Clerical Workers Organizing Campaign Records (TAM 126)
Historical/Biographical Note
The Graduate Student Organizing Committee (GSOC) represents graduate and research assistants at New York University (NYU) and is affiliated with the United Auto Workers Local 2110. GSOC was the first graduate employee union at a private university to successfully negotiate a contract, in effect from 2001 to 2005, which included major improvements to stipends, benefits and employee rights. In 2004 the National Labor Relations Board reversed the legal precedent of the Brown University decision, which required private universities to negotiate with graduate employees. NYU administration then refused to bargain with GSOC after the expiry of the first contract, leading to a six month strike in 2005-2006. In 2013, following a GSOC petition to the NLRB to reverse the Brown University decision, the NYU administration announced that they would resume collective bargaining with GSOC on the withdrawal of the NLRB petition. GSOC remains the only graduate employee union at a private university in the United States.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains materials pertaining to the GSOC organizing drive from 1998 to 2000, and the negotiation of GSOC's first contract with NYU in 2001. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence, especially paper copies of emails sent on NYU graduate student listservs. There is a substantial amount of correspondence from the Graduate History Student Association and GSOC listservs, and from organizer Jane Rothstein. Other materials include promotional flyers, newsletters, handwritten notes, surveys and labor education materials. There is also research material about graduate student organizing at other universities in the United States.
This collection does not contain material pertaining to the 2005-2006 strike, or GSOC's campaign for recognition following the NLRB reversal of the Brown University decision.
Web based materials date from 2009, focused on press coverage of the union, healthcare initiatives, solidarity statements and resolutions, bargaining information, and information on resources for graduate student members.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Adjuncts Come Together - United Auto Workers (ACT-UAW) in 2003. The accession number associated with this gift is 1950.177.
http://www.2110uaw.org/gsoc/index.htm was initially selected by curators and captured through the use of The California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service in 2009 as part of the Labor Unions and Organizations (U.S.) Web Archive. http://www.makingabetternyu.org/ was added in 2013. In 2015, these websites were migrated to Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. In April 2020, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1Hnwpdhxi-YcdELAXpSxEo1DtkAIOFyi9EL3t-A-wJ_k/edit?ts=5e70dd92 was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2020.027. https://docs.google.com/document/d/1htroirJ4BssAAnCbDiLbk_aLOLppQ850ajyfF0KODAA/edit, https://nyuawdu.wordpress.com/, https://collectiveactiongetsthegoods.tumblr.com/, and https://drive.google.com/file/d/1bN_qdmKsLQwJNaRQ2HvaVC1BsuVLK8UV/view were added in June 2020. The accession number associated with these websites is 2021.009. In July 2020, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1hJmaiHirFZ3QKgX-_khYTRu1ZpQZktpJN6-RW31By1o/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1vHXFMVVGbm4vpZ4tXo8qHHBSBj491RAeFnb3kQD9hAw/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1XSvLb8-v-bQKq_9NoTOcaFk69_zgIr0rf9kO2LTesPY/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1pobEs-21pqYViqBUGmd4AtDIjt5u1-gl-ovz0WGy3S4/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1l5XSNDxJb0aQlOdupblVjyIiriI9rD-YNKJOYLHYsxM/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/10Zpd507HIOXe8guurtjjn2wBUW5YCpzoLluCz0MN28I/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/19vcWypqVL2JktNZP4udYD3UOR-6u_EeMhhQ-ayuGmVM/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1IGjRwSpqh_2febJRtbi9SjHI9iuoQy7iBrQkyGLhJzs/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/111-NDnAd0vcPujHRGwyCpz38tXMJUh1O5b16vf31teU/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1h23To3cX8ScNAMg1b-uQDz_7Gzx7fDNGWMY50jBa7L0/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/16h_fnM_BCs-WymCQBhFIjU7BUdS6GDsfL59ORTfvBbE/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1moPbJkYrpJ9rVBiuBAEAZCPTOF2CIrSbC0RUzJ8a9dI/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/15IC6Ab8AJqYFcNCrIW902Zy86xPMklxYjucHQ88TRbg/edit, and https://docs.google.com/document/d/1zXEEkKOlLVmBlLvkMl-AnTXIqR68akzk347Bhch4Bmg/edit were added. The accession number associated with these websites is 2021.013. In October 2020, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1jI3unOFvYyRZ4FphBBuxr34C6zfFwbLwOLkqfYsabE8/edit and https://docs.google.com/document/d/1T-nPlg-KYClv7T0INTTC0Z-OcRGPsT6RACML8h24lxM/edit were added. The accession number associated with these websites is 2021.048. In February 2021, https://drive.google.com/file/d/1xHwa0prf-lbQuAb8FIAREbQjCYe69NxW/view, https://drive.google.com/file/d/1TNjJ-JYj5KtO_kRgYkLR9ofndJrBZQJM/view, https://drive.google.com/file/d/18NYt38wemQiLL-f1zNi6gYmwoq6wmDnd/view, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1VTuBiK7st78YhnY60e1TTfrb0zGoHyhy-pfat1U4ktQ/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1uNvo6Mo-O3-Zzh6oXkKkTlo6vTCkfvxKdDaE4J0zf_w/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1T4Johc-a3GukR1E3jSzEhW5d-kcgBQvZDPhMIj3FMD0/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1rXqIvRRjwx1N8NKQJSXHhs33vTwUO0Wmciu95Kg2VAk/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1PwSdwUuKG8NbUNUz0auB-DxNHuEbCSZ2-gOastE6erI/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1PstG6yiqz0mbj-0ZDvEu0x8eX7rKDDqpo_PyXDBvqrg/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1o2KW7XeuH0FIbklLywM0Ek7q9QhlnwwFmTf6nh5EJuU/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1n6N9-SpitTvfUIbPYo4KK0Z7AsfIvMegFRXbaOo-eD8/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1M6rTlb02qXAfR18TnpHwDsgzfe-hs-0BoJYrWpJ9ep0/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1-itS4Mb-6StUWRdM-Bup16bporGmTr2wjJ_M62KdbTc/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1IJS-5B1qqmozYTbsT1257ACWDZL7hvXL-eUjY0GQKEY/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1H4fNWlilGAs6NBh6ayTn581FP8fOVQBbVQ6AJsYyWyg/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1-EoNxQxVkdwxH0avIp_0bi1LqPuZnTJu1Rtdb2_8GhE/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/16-LwmAY-UL8J6wRjQEEDrrwJwHW75ypoSQcTRVLzmvg/edit, and https://docs.google.com/document/d/12BkdDjE8nJ_Tm2qhwnkSLNzBCPXyIGxk1xbvBL-u9P8/edit were added. The accession number associated with these websites is 2021.068. In March 2021, https://twitter.com/GSOCUAW/ https://twitter.com/GSOCUAW/status/1309194688751185920/ were added. The accession number associated with these websites in 2021.077. In April-May 2021, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1N_o7L6-VBED0yVDZyg5yiLvQXHlrvM4l1XKChZpvjno/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1inFGKR1_BbPi3po5RYZjjnZnsjuHi3114nOk-nvKtJU/edit, https://drive.google.com/file/d/1pcDFgHle9EQBxFxru27LI-lXaGGV2PfS/view, https://drive.google.com/file/d/1R3IXRMxS1kB-GhwXam5awrmcztGcTnfe/view, https://drive.google.com/file/d/12gPWzgfZnm3Lu4k1WIz8DGdbe2TYzy_b/view, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1my9W6Svzzo9xiGvhX7hXO2ZvpQ_QzWq97hUBKAK8Vm0/edit, https://drive.google.com/file/d/1viUqbo29OmmskWGvBUi_Ic3rwY_rmxz6/view, https://drive.google.com/file/d/1nHMNe-35hT9Bgct81Q9rE7aKC2EPmfhG/view, https://drive.google.com/file/d/1kPOCZI49kxi0GmmQmKA6efqzIUPv6lTG/view, https://drive.google.com/file/d/1cT1QFevXzAK7Y4QxTBHmUA7AyR6cVszM/view, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1zXEEkKOlLVmBlLvkMl-AnTXIqR68akzk347Bhch4Bmg/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1zLB0M22EYr13u1Wztubq-crsCpzMq3nQrifPHdRsoro/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1zEdprYdiwppsqL1QGHS2Kez0d8fiMp1Vhlc4osbgL3A/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1YOdizd0c1LAXMiAqjDM53gJAM3BlPehwwm9m7Krtmv4/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1-VWNC4HCZ6YL7zpntu2ihvT-1WjFSrw0B6V7zU2igcY/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1u65QspGrQXtriYL_5O-CId1o0R3dFevlo7qGGWJKxfk/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1SfOY_Vc39_HkuyJ9HG8tjUvRnFfKxIoQTLVjoo-TkIg/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1S0NDy3NMcC_0J_U4HiWDxY4tOx-nyEis_zjjLtr9ulk/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1OXcGFyqoZe-u6JF1HXUu91WcIdY-SjYmrjSr5yUe6Ds/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1KFtjiMtOTnQBeWWCZpr2KKWWk0GmtoRsceVjGyTQJ98/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1GE1k6ZMLRO1UI_cDnTCqWDlhiBNnFrXdwXqXKm2KHHQ/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1FaECLWU97Py73BwLbQl6ZTMKcLFwlS4-wq53ZmKSxr0/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/19pgqCFoP64f8Nu1VJoBG-cD7TulsB1kt9dtyW2A43zs/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/19FtwMDvfhu-0VyfWFIQI4HS8fkaCDx9ADnOpeTZhCnk/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/18HsWSVj7cvEc6m7pastoeeWsH2pP2MKRZXcjz8mwHV8/edit, and https://docs.google.com/document/d/10FzKXjJaWBVHinaR6KNUaHt5g2DpY0SIPoYRr4zaT9I/edit was added. The accession number associated with these websites is 2021.085. In May 2021, https://drive.google.com/file/d/1kYrhZCG3kNxuHbaTz8lTfzGGXn48AcMS/view, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1zFxsIK0kqf9h7-TkK9csJAB1PA3SSGKfpMrZKU4tIyg/edit, https://drive.google.com/file/d/1ylArpHC7JjuoBYwvsqATOKVVtJgWfffM/view, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1ZZPiNo2qc6g9iQc44Rk4Uz0_ZkwJ4QsoM1eqUaxUbZM/edit, https://drive.google.com/file/d/1axHq2lCk-YS-ZBglXhiVnoNY5JmQv0YO/view, https://drive.google.com/file/d/1mBeoLYCwQHECXfxVILEJzd2yOXf_n5nE/view, https://drive.google.com/file/d/1jqLCnA35_FMZ7qHsWJf8ziaSEKOL_ORo/view, https://drive.google.com/file/d/1CjLCFEQh8o7_kupmRoSi9YELYUPs-4_a/view, https://drive.google.com/file/d/1HVqV5cqUBVBNBGAOQcGD92vx_w0PHxrk/view, https://docs.google.com/document/d/152h35uGb_7CfZCa4nPlEUthvtIDJJKh14dhlBy7s2HY/edit, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1tSluyEsSFXH7Ad_8g6NpT7RcIA9QSlUXLXK0iuZT6_4/edit, https://drive.google.com/file/d/1DNBPf4XElIh1it9REeQq7e8Wjhj_TBdm/view, https://drive.google.com/file/d/1Rx4-ucSyN_ypCAIi5-12Hz8UuOftoodw/view, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1Abzd87NFEs4dFS9rYyqrOrQMWsvQRjHqi-XHbcKStZU/edit, https://drive.google.com/file/d/1ez54z0r8Uq_8uGRvsDWnC9SlQzp8XdSS/view, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1pB6-eWsM90A7SiYkuMZxJ2H-m5rETPXnQaEkzJ0OtNM/edit, and https://docs.google.com/document/d/1YYkdKZcYSG7bP6OgAZAT2mh7ciLhvzuQ6znvvAGntNs/edit were added. The accession number associated with these websites is 2021.088. In March 2022, https://docs.google.com/document/d/1rGpsnPVa5B3pwxSSWq2HlbEg2gX5pJfLME3LotsPL_4/edit was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2022.048.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into two series. Materials in Series I are arranged alphabetically by topic.
Series I: Records, 1996-2003
Series II: Archived Websites, 2009-ongoing
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Graduate teaching assistants -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Collective bargaining -- New York (State) -- New York.; Coalition of Graduate Employee Unions; Yale Graduate Students Union; United States. National Labor Relations Board; New York University; Adjuncts Come Together-United Auto Workers (ACT-UAW)
- Series I: Records, 1996-2003
  - Admissions and Funding Policy, 1997-2000; cuid9007 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Federation of Teachers, 2001-2002; cuid9008 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Committee Meetings, 1998-1999; cuid9009 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: Coalition of Graduate Employee Unions, 2000-2002; cuid9010 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: Faculty of Arts and Science, History Department Listserv, 2000; cuid9011 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence: General, 1999-2002; cuid9012 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Graduate History Student Association Listserv, 1998-1999; cuid9013 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Graduate History Student Association Listserv, February 2000; cuid9014 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Graduate History Student Association Listserv, March 2000 - December 2000; cuid9015 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Graduate History Student Association Listserv, 2001-2002; cuid9016 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Graduate School of Arts and Science, Graduate Student Council Listserv, 1999-2000; cuid9017 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Graduate Student Organizing Committee, United Automobile Workers Listerv, 1998-2000; cuid9018 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Graduate Student Organizing Committee, United Automobile Workers Listerv, 2001-2003; cuid9019 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Jane Rothstein, 1998-1999; cuid9020 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Jane Rothstein, 2000; cuid9021 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Jane Rothstein, 2001-2002; cuid9022 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: New York University Administration, 1999-2002; cuid9023 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: United Automobile Workers, 1999-2002; cuid9024 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Frequently Asked Questions, 1999, undated; cuid9025 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Graduate Employees and Students Organization (Yale University), 1996-2000; cuid9026 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Graduate Organizing: Other Universities, 1996-2002; cuid9027 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Graduate Students Against Unionization, 1999; cuid9028 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Graduate Student Rosters, 1999-2000; cuid9029 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Labor Education, 1999, undated; cuid9030 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Letters of Support, 2003; cuid9031 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous, 1999; cuid9032 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - National Labor Relations Board, 2000; cuid9033 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Newsletters (Adjunct Voice and GSOC Journal), 1999-2003; cuid9034 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Notes, undated; cuid9035 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Posters (Oversize), 2000-2002; cuid9036 (Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS003, Folder 1)
  - Press Coverage, 1999-2001; cuid9037 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Promotional Fliers, undated; cuid9038 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Sign-Up Sheets, undated; cuid9039 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Surveys, undated; cuid9040 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Unionization of Intellectual Workers (Articles), 1997-2000; cuid9041 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Video (Adjuncts Coming Together) [2 VHS copies], undated; cuid9042 (Box 1, Cassette cuid9042)
  - Video (NAFTA - Eye-Witness) [1 VHS copy], 1999; cuid9043 (Box 1, Cassette cuid9043, E-records tamwag_wag285, E-records cuid9043)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Format: VHS, Duration: 13 min.
- Series II: Archived Websites, March 2009-ongoing; cuid9044; 13 websites in 13 archived websites.
  Scope and Content Note
  The Graduate Student Organizing Committee (GSOC-UAW Local 2110) is the union for graduate employees at New York University (NYU) and the Polytechnic Institute of New York University. This includes teaching assistants, research assistants, and graduate assistants. The Polytechnic Institute organizes science and engineering graduate students. The union was established in 1998 and negotiated their first contract with NYU in 2002. In 2004, the National Labor Relations Board reversed the Brown University decision, declaring private universities are not required to bargain with graduate employees and leading to NYU not negotiating a new contract. Capture of the website began in 2009, which contained information on the history of GSOC, their contract, press converage, press releases, member information, and action campaigns. Capture of http://www.makingabetternyu.org/ began in 2013, containing information about the union and its Polytechnic Institute (later Tandon) affiliate (SET-UAW), campaigns, news, healthcare petition, and event listings. Over time, the website has been updated to include their current contract, bargaining information, solidarity statements and resolutions, caucuses, and documentation on the union's response to the COVID-19 pandemic and demands to NYU administration to support graduate student workers.
  This series also includes the websites for the New York University Academic Workers for a Democratic Union the social justice caucus of GSOC. https://collectiveactiongetsthegoods.tumblr.com/ contained their principles, 2014 bargaining report, statements of solidarity with other striking graduate students unions, bargaining updates, information on elections and strikes in 2014-2015, and news from the union. https://nyuawdu.wordpress.com/ was captured starting in 2020, when GSOC began bargaining for a new contract. The website contains their bargaining platform, bargaining committee members, updates, and fliers.
  Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
  Accruals
  Site crawls are accrued semiannually.
  In 2020, https://makingabetternyu.org/ was accrued monthly.
  Appraisal
  Crawl was limited to domains and subdomains of https://www.makingabetternyu.org/ and https://nyuawdu.wordpress.com/ in order to remain within the collection scope and data constraints.
  Scope was expanded to include Google documents.